<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="owl_mach_ipc_unstable_v1">

	<copyright>
		Copyright © 2019-2021 Sergey Bugaev

		Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a
		copy of this software and associated documentation files (the "Software"),
		to deal in the Software without restriction, including without limitation
		the rights to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense,
		and/or sell copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the
		Software is furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:

		The above copyright notice and this permission notice (including the next
		paragraph) shall be included in all copies or substantial portions of the
		Software.

		THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR
		IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY,
		FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND NONINFRINGEMENT.  IN NO EVENT SHALL
		THE AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER
		LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING
		FROM, OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER
		DEALINGS IN THE SOFTWARE.
	</copyright>

	<interface name="zowl_mach_ipc_v1" version="1">
		<description summary="communicate over Mach IPC">
			This protocol allows the client and the compositor to set up a connection over
			Mach IPC using the Mach bootstrap server. This may be useful for a number of
			reasons, including sharing resources that can only be shared over a Mach IPC-based
			API.

			This protocol does not, by itself, assign any meaning or semantics to the Mach ports
			it creates. In order for any port to be actually used for any concrete task, it needs
			to be assigned a role, which determines what other operations (such as MIG routines)
			are valid to be used on it.

			See owl-iosurface for an example of a protocol that makes use of owl-mach-ipc.
		</description>

		<event name="bootstrap_name">
			<description summary="announce the bootstrap name">
				By sending this event, the compositor announces the bootstrap service name
				it uses. The client is then expected to look up the compositor's Mach port
				using a call such as bootstrap_look_up().
			</description>
			<arg name="name" type="string"/>
		</event>

		<request name="create_port">
			<description summary="create a Mach port">
				This request creates a zowl_mach_ipc_port_v1 object that wraps a Mach port
				that is usable for communication between the server and the client. This request
				by itself does not create the underlying Mach port of the zowl_mach_ipc_port_v1
				object. In order to create or otherwise get the underlying Mach port, the
				zowl_mach_ipc_port_v1 needs to be assigned a role first.
			</description>
			<arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="zowl_mach_ipc_port_v1"/>
		</request>

		<request name="destroy" type="destructor">
			<description summary="destroy zowl_mach_ipc_v1">
				Destroy this zowl_mach_ipc_v1 object and all the resources associated with
				it. Destroying a zowl_mach_ipc_v1 object while a Mach port that was created
				using it is in use is an error.
			</description>
		</request>
	</interface>

	<interface name="zowl_mach_ipc_port_v1" version="1">
		<description summary="Mach port">
			This interface represents a Mach IPC port. To create or otherwise get the underlying
			Mach port, as well as to make use of it, this object needs to be assigned a role
			using some other protocol (such as owl-iosurface).

			After this object has been assigned a role, the client can retrieve the underlying
			mach_port_t (as a send right) using the	owl_mach_ipc_v1_retrieve_port() MIG routine,
			passing the port obtained from the bootstrap server and the secret sent by the server
			in the zowl_mach_ipc_port_v1.secret event.
		</description>

		<event name="secret">
			<description summary="announce the secret key">
				This event announces the secret key that the client can pass into the
				owl_mach_ipc_v1_retrieve_port() MIG routine in order to retrieve the underlying
				mach_port_t of this zowl_mach_ipc_port_v1.

				The secret key is both a security measure that prevents other processes from
				impersonating the client, and a way for the compositor to know which
				zowl_mach_ipc_port_v1 instance the port is requested for.
			</description>
			<arg name="secret" type="string"/>
		</event>

		<request name="destroy" type="destructor">
			<description summary="destroy zowl_mach_ipc_port_v1">
				Destroy this zowl_mach_ipc_port_v1 object and all the resources associated
				with it, including the underlying Mach port, if it is still valid.
			</description>
		</request>
	</interface>
</protocol>
